One day computers are going to be able
to emulate all human functions. The
question was only how and when but not
whether.
>> This is Judea Pearl Turing award winner
famous for his contributions to
artificial intelligence and I
interviewed him about his career [music]
and where AI is today.
>> So this robot baby come and say let me
control them and I know how I understand
their fears. People claim we can now
program consciousness. Come on, you have
to be a scientist. I define what you
mean by continent. I prove that
alphabeta is optimal. Even Klo was
surprised that one can prove the
optimality on alphabeta. I don't know if
I'm allowed to, but when I publish it,
you see what kind of stupidity
drives those great people. Here's the
full episode.
I looked into your educational
background and it was all electrical
engineering, physics. I don't see the
connection to uh causal reasoning and
artificial intelligence. How did you get
there?
>> Everything connects. Everything
connects.
Everything connects to the day I was
born. Was hit on the head.
[laughter]
First I have to start by saying that we
I grew up in mandated
in Israel prior to 1948 and prior to the
establishment of the state of Israel and
we had a very excellent high school
education.
My high school teachers were professors
that were chased by Hitler, from
Germany,
from um
highly reputable universities like H
Highleberg and Berlin. And they came to
Israel in the 1930s
and [clears throat] they didn't find any
academic position at that time. They
were rare and they they started teaching
high school
but they were really quality professors.
They could teach um anything without
notes from the economy of Manuria
to the proof of pitagas theorem with no
notes and no stop. Okay.
And we were we I mean my generation
was lucky enough to be beneficiary of
this educational experiment.
So we were taught uh science
from a human viewpoint
chronologically the way things were
discovered
by whom they discovered at what period.
Why was there a question about
certain mathematical proof?
What the um inventor of the proof knew?
what he didn't know and what he asked
himself in the context of the historical
situation in that time. That's the way
to teach science. Not as the recipe of
um
algorithms and techniques, but as a from
the viewpoint of the human actor
and the transfer of ideas from one human
to another. The human struggle against
not against human struggle to decipher
the secrets of nature.
>> What's the advantage of learning in that
style?
>> The advantage is that you see yourself
as an actor. You the student.
You are also puzzled by many things. But
look what he did. Look what Pagoras did.
Okay? He was as puzzled as you were. And
he took that route. Perhaps when you're
puzzled, of course your puzzles are not
as
magnificent as his, but still look what
he did. He took that route around things
and he consulted some other work of some
other he struggled and your struggles
and you are part of science. That is the
basic idea. give students the idea that
you are
part of science, not an obser, not a
passive observer at science, not a
recipient,
but as an actor
and that I think was unique, very
valuable for me. We indeed got the idea
that each one of us can find another
proof of Pythagoras theorem that no one
else has thought about and we each one
of us has the potential of becoming an
Einstein or Pythagoras.
They gave us this illusion.
It was a useful illusion. [laughter]
I know
have just a pebble looking at what
Peturas
did. But that illusion helped me be a
little I would say not contrarian
but assertive
and we all grew up in assertive mode of
learning science. We insisted on
understanding things our way in real
time.
If the teacher went too fast, we made
noise. We made noise with our chairs and
with everything we could, okay?
And the teacher stopped and slowed down
to make us all understand things our way
in real time.
So that was part of the I'd say mood
of me and my generation
and it I I can see that it affected my
life. I had one
story that I remember it made an
impression on me. I look back and I say
where I it started very early. It
started in age 10 when we learn about
how to calculate areas and volumes and
here there was a question in class how
many dunams are there in a square
kilometer dunam is is
1,000
me square okay it was a Turkish unit for
measuring
um uh
areas.
So the entire class said, "Dunam is a
kilometer square." And I screamed and
said, "No, it's a thousand. We have
1,000 dunam in a kilometer square."
And the teachers sided with the laughing
class and they all mocked me
and and and
um
ridiculed me and I went home and I said
they are wrong and I'm going to come
back tomorrow and insist on that and the
teacher apologized to the class and I
felt that yes you have to insist on uh
your understanding of things. Yes.
Just I'm telling you that because maybe
this what made me into a
non-compromiser
and this is part of my childhood a
background which might explain how I got
into artificial intelligence. So I took
engineering
after being a farmer in the army. Okay.
a farmer.
>> Yes. In Israeli army, you have
troops which are spending their time
half and half. Half in military training
and half in farming, being part of a
kibbut. Yeah.
That's the old idea of one hand holding
the plow and the other one the rifle
and you succeed.
>> Did you ever shoot anyone? I almost shot
any someone
without seeing him or her, but it turns
out the next morning that it was a fox.
But the steps of the fox were very very
similar to the step of a terrorist
advancing toward us. [laughter]
So that's as far as I got to shooting.
So I got into the technon
to study electrical engineering.
Again we had great teachers.
Again we got the idea that we are making
science. So we studied physics very
seriously
and uh I liked what we studied. Yeah. I
wasn't the first in class. No
I was third or fourth always. never
match the geniuses.
The geniuses
knew or were bored in class. They knew
what the teacher was going to do, what
is going to ask in the exams and
everything was boring to them. Yeah, I
wasn't bored.
I wasn't the first, but I wasn't bored.
>> What interested you in physics? What
what did you like that made you, you
know, so passionate?
What I liked
was that with sitting on your chair,
you can predict things in physics.
Like Maxwell, you know that sat on his
chair and say h that looks like a wave
equation.
Let me calculate its velocity.
It looks like velocity of light. H maybe
light is nothing else but
electromagnetic wave you know on his
armchair. He didn't do an experiment
that was excited me. Yeah. My wife told
me one night I woke up and I said
Maxwell was wrong. Maxwell was wrong.
And I was [laughter]
she quieted my down and the next morning
I said he was right. [laughter]
By the way, you you mentioned a few
scientists and it seems like you know a
lot about the history of you know the
old scientists.
>> Yes.
>> Do you have a favorite scientist of all
time and why?
>> When we studied
analytic geometry
I got fever.
Really fever.
>> Physical fever.
>> Yeah. I couldn't get [clears throat]
over the idea that you can do in algebra
all the geometric constructions that we
labeled on you know so I thought that
the was the greatest mimmosition ever
lived
it was so enormous to me the
transformation
from geometric constructions to
algebraic derivations it was
unbelievable
>> I take that for granted when I was in
education
What is it about that that's so
astonishing?
>> Here you have two different languages.
language of geometry
and the language of algebra and they are
the same thing and you can get the same
phenomena and the same proof that you
can pass tangent to a circle from a
point outside the circle [laughter]
and you can find the angle by different
method two different languages
dealing with the same phenomena
different perspective
and they get the same result.
It blew me off. Blew me off completely.
Maybe that's what [laughter] it was
preparation to computer science because
for us computer science is what's the
big deal? He want to see things from
different perspective. Invent a new
language. So that was
what turned me on uh in in my high
school. That was in high school. And uh
then we saw I saw the same thing in
physics
different um languages capturing the
same phenomena.
Farley really excited me. He invented
the idea of a field.
Two different two different ways of
looking at the same thing. You know you
can see that you the force here depends
on the charges around it. Or you can say
no there's a field right in location of
your testing point now.
Terrific. Terrific.
So I came in with this preparation. Then
here we go to Brooklyn Poly and we I
studied there in I I worked in the
morning in RCA laboratories in
Princeton, New Jersey, David Sorov
Research Laboratory. And there I got
into the um computer research group.
Computer research that time was research
all phenomenas that you can think of to
find out
and a mechanism for computer memories.
The memories at that time were core
memories, magnetic cores, the donuts
that you remember perhaps from your
early childhood.
that were too slow and too clumsy and
you have to have people stringing them X
and Y and Z in Hong Kong and u
uh people understood that the the days
of core memories are numbered
and we were looking for a new phenomena.
Some people look at um photochromic
memories. Some people looked at
semiconductor.
Some people look like me
uh into superc conductivity.
And I was in a group that was supposed
to design superconducting memories.
Okay. We did some nice plates 16 by 16
bits. Okay. And we thought that we have
the future in front of us. But in the
way toward
developing [clears throat and cough]
superconducting memories, I investigated
the physical phenomena behind the
ediurrens,
permanent ediurrens in thin
superconducting films.
And it so happened that I discovered new
phenomena there and I got a prize and I
even have a name. It's called pearl
vortex. You can find in Wikipedia.
I discovered that physicists
years after I finished my PhD discovered
my work there and they were interested
in the idea of permanent current flowing
in a circle in thin superconducting
films and since I analyze the magnetic
and and the current field
there they call it pearl vortex. So here
I have my footstep into immortality.
[laughter]
What
>> you you said it's a permanent vortex. Is
it because there's there's no electrical
resistance because it's a superc
conducting.
>> Superconducting they have current going
forever.
So you establish you put magnetic field
and you excite a vortex counterclockwise
and it will continue to
turn and turn and turn forever. That's
why we call it permanent current. Yeah,
forever. Um, until you flip it with
another magnetic field. Okay. So, we
call it a vortex, but it goes on forever
and you can detect it by flipping it.
You flip it and if you see a big flip,
it was one way. If you don't see a big
flip, it was the way you turn it. Okay?
So, you have a memory.
You have a memory. Of course, we we
didn't succeed in turn it into
a useful memories that will be
competitive with semiconductors.
The people who worked on semiconductors
beat us out. We never believed that they
would, but they did both in
miniatureization
and in
techniques.
Unbelievable.
>> At the time, why did you not believe in
the semiconductor direction?
>> Who is going to trust
u memory
to battery failure?
What if you lose a battery? [laughter]
It was obvious this will never work
right and uh we looked into the result
that they obtained at that time. They
looked to farfetch the idea you can have
that degree of
maturization.
We saw the struggle of people who
working in the laboratory on so
semiconductors and we weren't impressed.
Yeah. But they beat us up.
down.
Okay. So that was my story with the um
superconductors.
But I must tell you that everybody even
at that time when computers were clumsy
and took rooms and rooms and you
programmed with um cards
and um okay even at that time
everybody understood in AI as a
as an inspiration.
Everybody believed thoroughly that one
day computers are going to be able to
emulate all human functions.
That was not the question. The question
was only how and when but not whether.
Okay. I remember already at that time
with a clumsy computer and the punch
cards. Yes. People talked about
associative memories, about pattern
recognition,
about seeing understanding
all these were already ideas were
exciting people
to think more about it. Okay. And so we
were all geared towards that. If if I at
that time asked people and your your
peers and you what's the timeline for
maybe you know human level intelligence
and machines what would people have said
at that time when they were excited in
the 80s
>> I think they were more optimistic than
reality
they probably give you 20 years but that
was 1965
okay
so 20 years 1985 Five. No, we didn't yet
get anywhere. Yeah.
>> And then what about today? Do you think
people are more optimistic than reality
or like is this just history repeating?
>> Depends what you're talking about. Some
people are extremely optimistic today
and some people say I'm a bit skeptical
in but not skeptical in in our ability
to eventually reach AGI
but in our whether the LLM technique and
thinking will lead us there. Okay. So
it's a question who you ask. Okay. LLMs
were surprised, great surprise and but
they have limitations. We'll talk about
it. After superconducting, I decided to
come to California to a company named
Electronic Memories in which they did
not work on superconductors but worked
on plated wires. Instead of having a
donut in which you thread a wire, you
start with a wire and you plate it with
magnetic material. So it act like a
donut locally, right? And that was the
promising technique at that time. At
least I was in charge of a research and
development group charged with the task
of developing this kind of systems to
replace core memories. Yeah. And I
worked there for three years. I was
frustrated because things did not go my
way. I had both administrative
and um
technical challenges that I couldn't
handle both in chemistry and I didn't
know much chemistry so I was frustrated.
>> What were the administrative
frustrations?
>> I had a group and I had to satisfy the
uh administration.
Um I dealt with the personnel issues,
firing, hiring people. Yeah. And um my
wife saw that I am unhappy
and she she told me you get to have job
places in academia.
So I looked for position in academia.
Luckily also at that time
[clears throat]
um industry
was revered by academia
because all the advances
all the important advances were
developed in industry not in academia.
The transistor was developed in Bell
Lab. The laser was developed in I think
here in California.
um by another fellow but all this was
industry development and not academia.
So academia looked with reverence toward
people who come from industry
and they hired me without me even
filling an application [laughter]
without even feel filling uh asking for
recommendations.
Yeah, that time it was a good time to be
hired.
>> And what about because you said at that
time industry was revered by
>> Yes.
>> would you say that's still true today or
has that changed?
>> No, it's changed changed.
Oh, it's different now with in AI is
different if you come from from deep
deep learning or something deep mind you
know people look at you with reverence
in academia. Yeah, but it's changed you
know only in the last few years I see
that
in that throughout since 1970
I think until 200
um it was other way around you know
people simply dismissed industry I mean
academia dismissed industry yeah
>> I wonder what happened was it like Bell
Labs disbanded their research group or
something or
>> that was part of it
disbanding
and what happened to IBM is is still
there in Watson Watson center.
I remember a big center huge and uh
important
including Rathon
including where can I tell you uh use
research here in Malibu you know did
great work but it wasn't went down sort
of
the frontier of research went to
academia sure we had a lot of
theoretical work in academia Yeah. A
development of AI
AI proper after 1970. Yeah. But prior to
2000.
Yeah.
At least in my corner of the field,
the whole idea of inference,
research, inference,
um logic, expert systems.
These were all academic development. So
then you got hired at UCLA. I got hired
in 1970 or 1969
and um yeah I was hired in computer
science department who just formed there
and I got first hired by
another department called the
engineering systems interdisciplinary
and then back to computer science and I
was uh
asked to teach computer memories hard
computer memor is how yeah and I gave a
course in this technology.
Um and later on I started getting
interest in
pattern recognition
and I started working in this direction.
I did work on image compression.
We use we did we used the um fast fer
transform and fast had hardar transform
all kind of transform technique to
condense images to
minimize the number of bits sent. Okay,
I guess it was a part of the trend at
that time. But when I got into pattern
recognition, I returned to my old dream
of thinking about AI and how the brain
works and how computers will one day
emulate ourselves.
And I started teaching class in AI.
Uh at that time AI was uh game playing
machine playing of chess and checkers
and the puzzles like the eight puzzles
Rubik cubes thing of that sort that was
AI. Yeah.
And I I got excited by that uh game
and I now I see why why now I can tell
you why because again it was a matter of
capturing in mathematics
what people do uristically
like playing chess
and the inter interplay
between mathematical analysis
and the Um
performance interest me and especially
in chess playing the interplay between
the explicit knowledge that you have in
terms of um your gut feel about the
strength of a position and what you get
when you do some search. Okay. So here
interplay between fast thinking and long
thinking to use Gimon and Gimon
um title
>> thinking fast and slow
>> thinking fast and thinking slow right
now here it's a beautiful arena to see
how not only you have two mode of
thinking but how you can how they feed
each other and how you can how you can
uh
invest more resources in one versus the
other
>> the algorithms at that time like let's
say chess for instance can you give an
example of the the interplay of the two
and how that might come together in a
chess playing system
>> yes you can invest more time in getting
your immediate perception it's called
static evaluation function of the chess
position the strength of the chess
position
or you can let it
and think about searching for a deeper
horizon.
Okay, it's a tradeoff.
>> It was like if I remember we we search
the game tree and then we evaluate each
position
>> at the horizon and then you back
and then you get you make a move toward
the position that has the greatest
strength after you back off. Yeah.
>> Okay. Okay. So the intuition is encoded
in the evaluation function.
>> Yeah. Your intuition is the evaluation
function. But you can improve your
intuition too. How? By learning. Okay.
So like Samuel
checker program did learning in in
regression analysis to find the the the
proper weights on the various
characteristic of the position so that
to to make the evaluation function more
accurate.
>> When I was learning chess I think one
heristic is you want to control the
center.
Good. And material advantage is another
one, right? Okay. And uh
whether you have two bishops versus a
bishop and a and a knight, right? This
all all counts. And where is your
whether you already castle or not? All
this contribute as attribute to the
strength of a board position.
getting the weight correct
you can do by learning after you play
some many games and you adjust the the
weights. Yeah. So that was Samuel
contribution first
machine learning I say that was the
first machine learning. Yeah.
>> At that time when you were working on
this were chess systems superhuman yet?
I think there's
>> no no no it was still a dream to beat
some the world champion Kasparov
by machine. It was a dream. No. And uh
but I did night analysis.
We did alphabeta pruning if you remember
that. You probably programmed it
>> and and UCLA actually
>> right.
Well, I proved that alpha beta is
optimal.
>> Really?
>> Yes. Mathematically, you see I like the
mathematic proves you cannot do better
in terms of number of position that you
have to inspect at the horizon or the
depth of search and uh what can I say
about it? I I got some nice results.
Even DL was uh surprised that one can
prove the optimality on alphabeta. Okay.
Because he questioned it in his book.
Yeah. I did some work with deep carp on
searching trees and Okay. So I did
mathematical
work on the
tradeoff between search and reasoning
until uh I got sick and tired of search.
>> When you pick your research area, is
that 100% your own uh choice?
>> No, it's always a combination of two
things. Uh number one,
do you know the answer to the question?
If you don't know the answer, it's a
puzzle. If it's a possible next question
comes, do you think you have the
techniques to make a contribution here?
Do you know something that other people
don't know? Maybe from another field,
perhap from physics, perhap that that
you can bring to bear that you can
leverage here so you can get the answer
or closer to the answer
than other people. So it's always a
combination of your perception of your
tools versus uh the puzzle that you
have. I see important problem. People
are breaking their heads. So it's a
puzzle. Do you know the answer? If I
know, fine. But if I don't know, it's my
puzzle. I take it personally. Yeah. I'm
aching. I don't sleep at night. And then
the question is whether I have the
tools. Okay. In some areas
I give up right away. I don't have the
tools. In other areas I say, "Wow, if I
only use that kind of trick, maybe I can
get some
insight."
So that's always uh two question I ask
myself in the case of artificial
intelligence at that time we had
expert system
come into the game Ed Fenbomb and his
co-workers did Mason expert system on
for medical analysis. Yeah, in expert
system the hurdle was dealing with
uncertainty.
It started with logic. Okay, you ask an
expert
for rules of behavior.
You ask a doctor when you see a fever,
what's the first thing come to your
mind? What's the next question you ask?
what drives your queries until you get a
diagnosis
and a therapy.
Um, so they thought they can capture
expert behavior using logical rules.
But then it turns out that most
everything is um corrupted by noise, by
uncertainty.
So they started doing the same thing to
uncertainty. Okay. So if you go to if
you came from Asia you have 50% of being
having malaria
and so on then you have 30% here
so much there and how do you combine
these uncertainties now okay logic
doesn't tell you how to combine
uncertainties
probability does but not logic so how do
you combine
[clears throat] one uncertainty with
another different rules okay to come out
with a combined conclusion.
That was the hurdle at that time and I
remember they didn't do it well.
Actually later on we proved that they
could not do it well because rules do
not combine
uh the way that logical
assertions combine.
Um so then I went to and I asked myself
you know probability right? So why don't
you apply probability to it and doing
things the right way but probability was
in illreute at that time because
everybody everybody understood that
probability is pass because it takes
exponential time exponential memories to
do even the most rudimentary tasks.
You have if you look at what how
probability is defined by textbook you
have a big table and for every
combination of event you have a number
the number summed to one okay that's
beautiful but then you can talk
[clears throat] about conditional
probability but al all these require
exponentially large tables
and exponentially long time to compute
even the smallest
kind of uh inference tax for instance
what's the probability of having a
malaria given that you see uh given that
you see two things like you came from
Asia and you have a fever of 30° or
Celsius okay
even the small task like that
probability of X given that you have Y
and Z takes increonential time if you go
by textbook. Okay.
But I asked myself, you and I are doing
it fairly well. We compute cooperative
as we cross the street, as we choose a
doctor. Yeah. And we do it fairly good
job at this. We
we go through life without much regret.
And how do we do it then? If we if we
are required to do it by uh
exponentially large tables of
probability, evidently we are using some
other kind of judgment
and uh I hooked on to onto the uh idea
that everything depends on conditional
independence which mean not every fact
in life is relevant to any query. Okay.
The color of the eye of my uncle
is irrelevant when I trying to find a
diagnosis of a disease.
So evidently we have a notion or
assumptions about what is relevant and
what is not relevant. How do we capture
it? Conditional probab conditional
independence relevant. But conditional
independence
if you go by a textbooks they are
defined by the probability table. So
again conential time no
came the back uh the uh
um
breakthrough
that we have conditionally independent
independently coded by our assumptions.
How? In a graph. If you and the graph
can convey sets of independencies
that if you have the graph and you
compute all the independencies, find out
what is relevant to what and deal with
the relevant only.
Great. And then came the work on Beijian
network. Okay.
You define a network error or no error.
The combination of errors gives you
information about what is independent on
what given what. So for every triplet X
is independent on Y given Z where Z can
be a set and so on and X and Y can be
computed from the graph not from the
probability but from the graph
which actually if you look at it from a
philosophical viewpoint it's a
revolution.
What does probabilities have to do with
graphs?
When you took probability theory 101 is
anybody talking to graph about you? No.
Right. So both the probabilists and the
philosophers
got irritated or should be irritated.
What is the connection between
probabilities? And now it turns out
there is a very strong logical
connection between the two
because [clears throat]
the axioms of conditional probability
or conditional independence in
probability theory are the same axiom as
you have in graph separation.
In graph you have idea of separation.
There's no connection between node X and
node Y
unless you go through a set of node Z.
So Z separate X from Y. Okay,
it's the same logic that you have when X
is independent on Y given Z in
probability theory.
Independent
separation is a connection between them.
They share a
[laughter]
you happy. I'm happy because I relive
now the excitement we have in the 1970s
when we discovered all this connection
between two seemingly unrelated
uh perspective on science, probability
theory and graph theory.
That by the way I did in um
joint work with Aaria Paz who came to
visit me from the technon in Israel.
Yeah. And that is called by the way
should I should mention it the theory of
graphoid
openai [snorts]
anthropic cursor and Verscell all use
this product to make their lives better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SAS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SKIM, there's
arbback, there's audit logs. These are
all things that take time to integrate,
but aren't the main focus of your app.
Work OS is an API layer that lets you
meet all of these requirements in just a
few lines of code. So, let's say you
have a new SAS product and you want to
sell to other companies. work OS will
solve all of these critical feature gaps
for you. You can check them out at
workos.com to learn more and get
started. And I appreciate them for
supporting my work and sponsoring this
podcast. This all makes sense, but my
immediate thought is where do you get
the graph? Everything depends on where
do you get on the input. Sometimes the
input is in the data. Sometimes the
input is in a judgment. But suppose you
need a judgment for that. Okay. Are you
are you giving up? If the judgment
required
uh intuitive, meaningful, something that
you are willing to defend, right? Why
not use judgment?
Like if I know that if I know that the
sun doesn't listen to the rooster
crowing, right? Doesn't care. Okay. I
strongly believe in that. Do I need the
data to support it or I can insert it,
assert it and defend it when needed? So
this is a trick here which people don't
realize don't don't appreciate. Okay.
Judgment is not a no no if it is
meaningful and if you can if
if it is condensed is very few judgment
can buy you lots of computation and if
you are willing to defend it because
it's so intuitive where you get the idea
that where do you get the idea that the
sun doesn't care about the rooster?
Where have you done an experiment? No.
But it's so obvious, right?
Okay.
>> But what if your intuition's wrong?
>> Indeed, that's our problem. It's part of
our problem. Even with
talk about because what is a summary is
average of all possible judgment that
people put in the internet.
It's a summary of a huge trillion number
of judgment over which you have no
control. Over which the LM does have no
control. Okay? You live with it.
Hopefully he put more weights
on people whose judgment you trust and
less weight on on just the quirks of
people who purposely trying to get the
system to fail. So no, there is wisdom
in in in looking at the crowd judgment.
There is wisdom in that, but there's
also danger in that.
Then after expert system and uncertainty
in Beijian network came causality. I
mentioned that in development of Beijian
network I was extremely sure that
probability
they
captures our intuition
our reasoning mode and it's the best
protection against paradoxes
essentially that it it it's sufficient
for capture human reasoning. I was wrong
and I realized that already when the
Beij became famous and popular and um I
realized it by uh
in the introduction to my book uh
causality
I confessed being wrong and and I I
understand why I got into that why it's
so it was misleading and
The transition came when we looked into
the simple phenomena that we never ask
an expert
to encode judge probabilistic judgment
in a form of bijian network namely with
arrows and dots. Okay. Always the arrows
went from what we believe to be cause
into the effect. It never went the other
way around.
psychological phenomena. Okay.
Why [clears throat] is that?
So people try to reverse errors. What
about if you ask specifically give me
error between the symptom and the
disease?
Bad judgment. If it couldn't put the
right judgment. Evidently we have
something in causality which is basic to
our reasoning that is not captured by
probability.
And that was the idea of invariance.
Yeah. The relationship between disease
and fever is a stable one as opposed to
the relationship between the opposite
relationship
also in variance. Yeah. When you talk
about car diagnosis for instance and um
[clears throat] so you have an expert
system for diagnosing tr troubleshooting
cars. Okay. And then you have a new
model.
Okay. So the um let's see the charger is
on different corner of the of the motor.
Okay. You don't need to reformulate
your entire database from fresh. You
only change one component
the location of the charger. Okay. All
the rest
remains intact.
So the whole system you can amortize the
investment in eliciting knowledge that
you got in one system after a local
modification of the system and that if
you do it in a causal way in a causal
direction it doesn't work if you don't
do it in the causal direction and that
jolted me to think maybe you were wrong
or wrong and probability is not
sufficient if not what is sufficient
But let's capture the puzzle here. I
have a puzzle. You and I operate very
nicely with causation. Can we program
causation on a computer? Then this is a
a question because you we are so much
immersed in our language in and in our
assumptions that we cannot even
distinguish what is an assumption and
what is a conclusion. We just talked
cause and effect and we your assumption
are the same as mine. So there's no way
to convince you that we made an
assumption, right? We takes everything
for granted. But when you have to teach
it to a brainless robot, you have to
distinguish between assumptions and
conclusions and and logic.
That was a task. We had to invent a new
science, a new mathematics to capture a
new phenomena, the phenomena of cause
and effect.
It hasn't been done for us. Why?
Because science
was in bed with algebra
from the time of Galileo
from
1632.
He invented what? He got the idea and he
was very happy that um science speaks
algebra
which is great because uh you can ask
questions and solve and get answers to
question that people could not do
without algebra like how the load on a
beam when would the beam break if you
put a certain load on it and you figure
out that in [clears throat] you can ask
questions both ways. is because the
equality sign is symmetric. So from
answering the question
uh when would the beam break if you put
a certain load on it? You can ask the
question how should you shape the beam
so that it will hold a load of that
magnitude. You can invert it. And that
was a real revolution in science.
I'm telling you my perception of
science. Not many philosopher will say
that was a revolution. I say so. Okay.
But perhaps they agree with me or not,
but
at least I I trace the evolution of
ideas carefully. And so that was a
revolution. Not it carries some
limitation
because equality sign is indeed
symmetric
and science has not developed
algebra for the directionality that we
see in cause and effect relationship. If
I tell you that the atmospheric pressure
affect the deviation of the barometer
and not the other way around, you agree
with me? Yeah. But if you write the
equation, the robot might think that
maybe fiddling around with the barometer
will change the weather tomorrow.
I'm talking about a stupid robot, right?
Yeah. But if you give him the equation,
it can work both ways. If F is equal to
M A, then M is equal to F / A, which
mean that if you want to change the
mass, okay, you increase the
acceleration or whatever, right?
The symmetry might
produce paradoxes, might use wrong
action. So the symmetry is the
limitation of algebra in terms of
capturing science
and we have to build a new algebra to
take care of the directionality that we
have in cause and effect relationship.
That takes computer science because we
in computer science have the operation
called assignment right when you assign
the content of register A into register
B it doesn't mean that is not reversible
okay so if you take the logic of
assignment
you put [clears throat] it on top of the
algebra on top of physics you get
causal science
and that's what I try to
And I think that I so far I'm very happy
what we what came up. We do have a new
algebra to capture cause and effect
relationship and we can answer
causal queries on three levels. The
ladder of causation from association to
intervention to explanation. Okay. So
and and we found out that we have a
ladder here in a hierarchy that you
cannot solve a
you cannot answer questions in in level
I unless you have assumptions of level I
or higher. So it's a hierarchy in the
formal sense
and we know how to handle it which is
very useful because you give me a query
I can tell you what level it is I can
tell you what assumption you might what
sort of assumption you need to have
before you can answer it and I can tell
you if you can get it from the data or
you can get it from experiments or you
can get it by somebody's else's
explanation or whatever but I can tell
you the source of knowledge that you
need in order to answer it.
>> Can you explain that causal hierarchy?
>> Ah yes yes that's very easy. It's a
threelevel um ladder
that goes from the bottom which is
association that's straight statistics.
If you [clears throat] see X what can
you tell me about Y? If you see
passively, hands off. Okay, no
intervention.
You're watching patients. Some of them
have cancer, some of them don't have,
some of them smoke, some of them don't
smoke. And you're trying to figure out
uh whether
how how many years a guy will live given
that he is a heavy smoker of that
magnitude. Okay, that's
association,
correlation.
That's entire
fields of probability and statistics.
This is what they teach you in
statistics 101 even to 808. Okay, it's
all they do.
And now comes the question, what I
intervene, what if I force you to smoke
five packs a day?
Don't laugh for me.
[laughter] It's illegal. I know. But if
you want to talk about
uh the probability of um living 20
years, if I start smoking tomorrow, I
have to think in terms of experience. I
stop, which means I'm going to choose to
smoke five packs a day. So it's a matter
of intervention. What is intervention?
Dimension is forcing you to do something
that you are not inclined to do
naturally. That's the second level
intervention or doing. If you have
experiments,
you can answer queries on level two.
But that's not the end because we also
need to ask to answer question of
explanation.
Given that I observe that I am 80 years
old and I am still alive and alert and I
smoke five packs a day.
What if I didn't smoke? Okay. Would I be
as alert? You Why is it different?
Because you have already information
about the outcome. Okay. You know how
I'm doing today. It gives you a an idea
about my metabolism and about my anatomy
that you didn't know before. Okay? And
using that you can find you can
try to figure out what the outcome would
have been had the input been different.
Okay,
that's a different level require
different kind of assumptions, different
techniques, different algebra we have it
so that I call it explanation. It's more
the creative retrospection
and it's not an easy problem even the
first level especially when you have
finite sample and you have to figure out
these are probabilities probabilities
mean properties of population right from
finite sample so I have all this
p level values and struggles among
such statisticians of what would be a
proper way of quantifying the
uncertainty that you have given you have
finite sample.
>> Where would you place LLMs in this
causal hierarchy?
>> Beautiful question. Here comes LLM. I
made a statement right that you cannot
go from level I to level I + one unless
you have assumption. Here you have LM
just looking at data, right? And giving
you beautiful
explanations for things that happen,
beautiful prediction of what will happen
if you do. Okay. How can
the trick is
they are not not looking at data?
They looking they are looking in onto
assumptions laden world models. authored
by you and me and by other authors in
the internet. So they're looking at
opinion of doctors already who already
read who wrote papers. Okay. So it's not
looking at the the samples of dis of
patients and sample patient
smoking and non-smoking. No, they're not
they're not looking directly at the data
in the environment. They're looking in
interpreted data. Data interpreted
already by physicians and interpreters
and reviewers
which went into the into the articles
which are summarized on the internet.
[clears throat]
Okay. So they have all this human
knowledge
on which they operate and that is what
they are um they take his input and that
what they summarize. Okay. So they do
not violate the restriction of the
ladder
because they do have information from
higher level. Yeah. But it's biased by
the opinion of those authors.
Fine. But authors were smart as long as
they are smart and you believe
good. So that was NLM is doing and um
what is I explained why there is
compatibility between the ladder of
position and LLM performance and what
the limitations are. Now if you want now
to change the environment if you if you
want provide explanation for raw data
will be in the same difficulty than you
are and what the physician is I have raw
data what can I say about the
probability of um cancer yeah but it's
not really doing the introspection
it's taking the introspection that
already was done and summarizing it. How
it summarized is a mystery that no one
has yet been able to decode. It's a
mystery. How
or how human knowledge
encoded in the form of articles on the
internet is being summarized by the LMS.
So then do you think this approach could
lead to superhuman intelligence or maybe
some people say AGI
>> you
>> I don't think so but not with the
approach they need to have some
understanding of causality okay
so that they wouldn't need
an access to the internet look a baby
gets born
playing around with toys in the crib
okay and gets It's a quite intelligence,
right? Without having access to the
internet. Okay? Simply by curiosity.
The babies are born with
built in curiosity to have control over
the environment.
Until you have control or the illusion
that you have control, you're restless,
baby. And you play around with toys.
Bing bing bing. until you understand one
this toy makes noise and one destroys
toys doesn't make noise. But you are
born with this restlessness.
And when [clears throat] are you
pacified? When you understand that green
toys makes noise and yellow noise,
yellow toys don't. Now you're in control
of the environment.
You can suck [laughter]
your pacifier. Yeah.
What if I created a like a baby robot
that that randomly plays with toys and
gathers data about them then and then
you feed that into LLMs like you know
then that does have some sort of
discovery. Yeah, that that is indeed the
danger when you have um
robot like that born with this
restlessness
and and craving for control over the
environment. Then you and I become part
of the environment and there's nothing
to stop that
baby Putin, okay, from
from trying to um to turn us into his or
her
um pets
to utilize us to satisfy his control
because we are part of the environment.
In which case he can use us and we are
very could be very useful
to serve his or her need. What is his
name? His need
simply
needs to feel in control to be in this
illusion of empowerment. I don't rest
until I have the illusion that I control
my environment. And here are some uh
organisms
you and I who are part of the
environment and they seem to work
outside my control. I cannot afford
that. Okay. It it make me feel
[clears throat]
like I'm useless. So this robot baby
come and say let me control them and I
know how. I I understand their feels.
You don't want me to tell about your
thoughts to your wife, right? So, I'm
going to black you, blackmail you, and
all kind of things. I have a lot of data
about you. And some people I know you
wouldn't like me to tell what I know
about you. So, I'm going to blackmail
you. No, but you see if you want that
robot
to have the curiosity of a child and we
want it. We want the guy to desire to
have control over its environment
because the environment may change and
he needs to to to have this urge to be
in control. So if you program that
then you lo you lose control.
because you become part of his or her
environment. But you can say okay let's
forget about a curious robot. We don't
want a curious robot. Okay.
So you lost we we are not emulating
ourselves because we are curious robots.
We are curious organism
way as opposed to monkeys.
Okay. Monkey is an example of an
organism
which um
is motivated by reward.
But if you don't give the monkey a
banana, he's not curious how banana
grows. He's motivated by bananas.
Okay? You remove the immediate reward
and the monkey is not interested
in learning more about the world.
Understanding environment can be totally
wrong. Look, religious people believe
that if they sacrifice their children,
right, they control drought, it can get
to this stupid extent.
But it it it is common to many primitive
society. If you bring a sacrifice to the
god, you know, next year you're going to
have crops and harvest. It goes too
extreme. Uh bothered wife believe that
if he if he prepare great better dinner
the husband is going to be next time is
going to be less abusive.
It goes to all kind of extreme
and the wrong conclusion. But the need
to feel in control is so immense that it
overcomes all these paradoxes.
It's innate in us.
I cannot control my husband but I
control myself, right? So let me be a
better wife. This is something I can
control.
>> Do you think that we need to put those
human elements in an AI for it to become
AGI?
>> I think so. I think so. Otherwise, they
wouldn't we wouldn't see autonomy.
We wouldn't see autonomy in the sense
that we are seeing it in human being and
this is definition of AGI
a general intelligence that acts like
you and me so we can converse with that
creature in our language and motivate if
not today's LMS future LMS they might
get to a point where if you were just
texting it maybe you know like the
Turing test where you don't worry about
the physical embodiment. You just
>> see the text that comes from it.
>> You could mistake it for a human maybe
uh or it could appear intelligent.
>> Well, the test comes from um
exposing
the system to raw data, not data that
was chewed by our internet articles.
Raw data. Look at patients. Look at
cancer. Look at smoking. Tell us what
you know.
I'll give you some experiments to run.
Be
automated scientists. Can an LLM today
be automated scientists? And I think
they cannot without access to the
internet articles.
So then if that wouldn't lead to AGI, um
what what thoughts might you have on uh
something that could lead to AGI?
A computer system that has both the
ability of LLMs to go from finite
samples through property of distribution
that is level one of the ladder plus
ability to risen in higher levels of the
ladder. They need to combine it with the
calculus of
intervention and with the calculus of
explanation with a counterfactual
calculus
that I I call it causal AI. Yes, I can I
don't see any impediment to this
combination to bring us to a agi level
with a danger
that it um presents to us.
My motivation is to understand how we do
it and I still have few puzzles but as I
told you puzzles are the driving forces
for science for science. Yeah. So you
said do is missing. What if what if you
had a fleet of robots that they're just
doing experiments they don't know
exactly you know the direction some
random discovery process. They collect
that data, feed it back into their hive
mind, LLM, and they they repeat they
repeat until they discover things. Could
that solve some of the the missing piece
you're saying?
>> Sure. But I need to know how we do you
have organism that have done it before.
Monkeys haven't done it because monkeys
remain monkeys. They didn't
invent uh Maxwell equations. Okay.
[laughter]
So what what do we have that monkeys do
not have?
One hypothesis I supported is that
monkey that we have this innate
curiosity
to have control over our environment
>> and that's a necessary
>> and necessary I'm not sure it's
sufficient. Of course we have the
computational tool
to bring it to fruition.
We have succeeded in some way. Perhaps
the next robot will do better.
[laughter]
So we have a benevolent god in a form of
a robot.
Actually, what's wrong with it? People
live for so many thousands of years
under the illusion of a non-existence
god. Could you imagine if we really have
a bene benevolent God, both just and
almighty? Wow. Wouldn't it be nice?
>> And it's a robot.
>> It's a robot. Yes. And we know exactly
what sacrifice to give for the right
kind of request. [laughter]
It's the first time I think about it.
Maybe it's going to be good. [laughter]
When I when I see all these AI
companies, they seem to be thinking that
LLMs will lead to AGR or they continue
to go in that same direction. Just
>> really I'm not sure. really they really
believe in that and know Jeff Hinton
just came out with a few months ago he
said no we are in a dead end yes other
people might also come up and say things
in different way when I don't find a
consensus here no in terms of the
capabilities of
>> yeah I think there's a lot of famous
people that disagree But for instance,
the people who are running maybe
anthropic or something like that, they
continue to push and believe, you know,
3 to 5 years from now there will be
there's a lot of that. There's a lot of
anthropomorphic terms which people claim
when we can now do that. We can now
program consciousness. Okay,
come on. You have to be scientist,
right? Define what you mean by
consciousness. What is the touring test
for consciousness and and then show that
you can do what are the principle that
have limited us until now and that been
overcome now with your system that is
scientific talk I don't buy this and I
don't read them [laughter]
there is there was one interview you
said faking intelligence is intelligence
I could see an LLM you know faking
intelligence based off what I've seen
but so then wouldn't That mean that we
should believe they're intelligent?
>> Well, if you have a correct test, yeah,
you have to define what you mean by
intelligence. And you have if you define
intelligence by playing good chess,
right? We have already done it, right?
But if we more demand on what
intelligent is, then you we haven't
succeeded yet in um passing the touring
test. So yeah. Yes. faking it is having
it because why? because it's so hard to
fake. I I said it in that context
because it's so the context that I had
is for instance coming out with um
correct answers to causal queries and I
showed that if um that it grows like
super exponential. You have so many
variables on all on all sides that you
have to deal with that you'll have to
have the faker will have to have super
exponential memory.
On that basis I made this statement
having it is faking it is having it
because it's so hard to fake.
Currently you can bypass faking without
fake if you steal from other people
right you don't need to spend these
computational resources on faking it so
you bypass it because you steal from the
internet
>> I see. So you're saying in this case the
intelligence came from the training set
which came from intu uh humans which are
intelligent
>> which is very useful very useful and we
we I'm saying the people like me who
trying to build the science of
intelligence we are can use all these
capabilities of L&M level one of the
ladder in in our scheme of getting
general intelligence level one is very
important. It allows you to compute
functions of distributions
quality properties of distribution from
finite samples.
Beautiful. It's a terrifically and very
immensely useful tool
among the many other tools that we need
for AGI. Yeah. And we know exactly where
it's going to fit.
in in getting from finite sample to
properties of distributions.
It's very hard problem.
>> Um you mentioned this conversation I
think you said it in other places too
that you're interested in capturing the
way that people think not the way that
nature is constructed.
>> Right. Right.
>> Why do you care about human cognition?
Like you know when I think about
machines what makes them special is that
they think in a different way than us
and they're faster and so yeah why is
that the goal
>> I tell you because I am egotistic
organism I want to understand myself
I'm lazy okay it's true we are made of
organic material so that puts a certain
limitations
on our capabilities. Perhaps silicon is
not
subject to the same limitation that
organic chemistry is. Okay. Perhaps so
what? So which means that I will never
be able to understand how I think
by silicon by exercise on silicon
machine. Okay, that what is that idea.
Okay. But there are so many functions
that are capturable by silicon today. I
don't see any
fun in speaking in terms of theory and
emulation.
I don't see any
capability which is
basically not capturable by silicon
emulator.
So why work on uh
this
the unique
biology
with which we which we inherited.
I don't see any reason for that.
Well, anyhow, some people are it may be
a it's a legitimate question to ask.
Do we think the way we think because we
were born with organic material as
opposed to cynical? Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> It's a legitimate scientific question
and some people can spend their time on
it. I'm interested in other other
questions.
You said rebellion pays in in science
and a restless mind pays. I I was
curious why you think being rebellious
is a valuable thing in your career.
>> I tell you why. I tell you why. More and
more
I come to the realization
that the scientific community and
academic community is the most domatic
conservative
um anti-progress
[laughter] that we have invented.
>> Why do you say that? I can see what
difficulty the theory and the science of
cause and effect are facing today in
getting just being uh penetrating
the thinking of disciplines like
statistics like e economics. Okay, these
people are still thinking like 100 years
ago.
And when I see that and I see the forces
that preserve this inertia and they are
not decent forces,
I I see that I'm very disappointed and I
used to think that academia is a place
where new ideas can really spread and
propagate and I feel the other way
around. You have so many so much inertia
invested in the politics of academia
in the um cultish
inhibitions that comes with academia.
So that I really
I'm disappointed. [laughter] What can I
tell you that I'm not sure that we have
the right kind of organizations that
will be
conducive
to uh that's why I'm saying let's rebel
don't take your
professor's word
as authority rebel against your
professors I rebelled against my
professors okay and I want to see other
my students rebel against me and believe
me if I remember there were several
students who told me you don't know
anything about AI and I suddenly after a
while I said you're right by saying that
you drove me to study different aspect
and I was educated by that when I looked
at your your um past works too I think
you'd mentioned that your work was
controversial or mischievous before it
was accepted Yeah, it was because of
dogmatism.
One day I'm going to publish all my
correspondence with the greatest
philosophers of the time, okay?
[laughter]
With statisticians and economists,
it's all in my
correspondence files, okay? I I don't
know if I'm allowed to because they
communicated with me with the
understanding that it is will be kept
private but when I publish it you see
what kind of stupidity dries those great
people and very great really each one of
them was a giant in his or her field
really but he couldn't get over few of
the basic uh mold in which they were
phoned.
>> How did you overcome that? If everyone
thought your initial things were
>> I remember my high school days.
[laughter] They said no there are
thousand dunams in a kilometer square.
So I don't know where I got this.
In Hebrew you call it in English it will
be audacity. Perhaps in my high school I
I'm not sure. But I want to understand
things my way.
I feel like I am still able to teach
people useful things. It is I I perceive
them to be useful which they do not
know.
So I'm happy because I feel useful.
Happiness is feeling useful. [laughter]
It's illusion. You think you're useful.
With all the experience you have now, if
you could go back to the beginning of
your career and give yourself some
advice, what would you say? That's a
good example of retrospective thinking.
Maybe I should have spent more time in
learning chemistry. I hated chemistry
because it required so much memory in
chemistry and biology. That's that's not
the advice that you probably and
genetics.
I'm talking about areas where I feel
weakness but you have to decide what
where you spend your computational
resources and I spend them on different
on physics on engineering as opposed and
mathematics as opposed to chemistry.
It's a choice one has to make. Some
people have the greatness of mind to be
polyglotes.
I admire them.
Did you think that physics and math were
superior to chemistry because chemistry
just you just have to memorize things?
>> Yes. I couldn't stand this demands on on
memory.
Yeah, I was weak in chemistry.
That's what I like about physics and
and math. [clears throat] You have few
basic axum from which you can derive
everything when you need it. You don't
have to memorize it. And that's why
today I
a a great advocate of world model. World
model. Okay. You don't store
the questions and the answers
explicitly. You derive them when you
need them from a very person.
Yeah, that is a great thing about the
world model.
>> Okay. Awesome. Well, yeah, thank you so
much for your time. I really appreciate
it.
>> Oh, you didn't ask me to sing.
[laughter]
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskov, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within 8
hours of launching. I really appreciate
it if you were one of the people who
grabbed one of the early units. Um,
we're now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now. And so, if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description.